<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC5598 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5598.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC5617 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5617.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6376 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6376.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6377 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6377.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC6541 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6541.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="exp"
        docName="draft-kucherawy-dkim-delegate-00">

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<front>
	<title abbrev="DKIM-Delegate">
		Delegation of Signing Authority with
		DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM)
	</title>

	<author initials="M. S." surname="Kucherawy"
	        fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy">

		<address>
			<email>superuser@gmail.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>

	<author fullname="D. Crocker"
		initials="D." surname="Crocker">
		<organization>
			Brandenburg InternetWorking
		</organization>

		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>675 Spruce Dr.</street>
				<city>Sunnyvale</city>
				<country>USA</country>
				<code>94086</code>
			</postal>

			<phone>+1.408.246.8253</phone>
			<email>dcrocker@bbiw.net</email>
			<uri>http://bbiw.net</uri>
		</address>
	</author>

	<date year="2014"/>

	<area>Applications</area>

	<abstract>
		<t> DomainKeys Identified Mail (DKIM) permits an agent to
		    affix a digital signature to an email message, associating
		    a domain name with that message with the strength provided
		    by a cryptographic mechanism.  The domain name thus
		    attached is not, however, necessarily the same as any
		    other domain name in the message.  In particular, the
		    domain need not match the domain found in the From field
		    of the message, though this is the one users typically
		    see and is thus typically considered the most important.
		    This decoupling means DKIM cannot be used to, for example,
		    confirm that a message signed by someone other than the
		    author is actually content generated by that author. </t>

		<t> What is needed is a way for an author to indicate that a
		    signature from some third party was anticipated by the
		    author, and thus a receiver can conclude the content
		    is legitimately from that author.  This document presents
		    a specific application of DKIM that can achieve that
		    goal. </t>
	</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
	<section anchor="background" title="Background">
		<t> DomainKeys Identified Mail <xref target="RFC6376"/> defines
		    a mechanism whereby a verified domain name can be attached
		    to a message, or portion of a message, using a
		    cryptographic signature.  It does not, however, assert
		    that this domain name matches a domain name found anywhere
		    else in the message. </t>

		<t> Author Domain Signing Practices <xref target="RFC5617"/>
		    was developed as an add-on to DKIM that establishes a
		    binding between the domain name validated by DKIM and 
		    the one visible in the From: field on a message.  In
		    essence, the ADSP test is satisfied if there exists
		    on the message a DKIM signature whose domain name matches
		    the one in the From: field of the message being checked.
		    For instances where this test fails, ADSP further offers a
		    mechanism for a domain name owner to publish via the
		    Domain Name System a policy statement requesting that a
		    mail receiver prevent delivery of the message. </t>

		<t> Use of ADSP by a domain that has actual users can create
		    problems for certain common applications.  One of these
		    is mailing lists, where strict use of ADSP can be
		    disruptive to mailing list operation (see Section 5.2 of
		    <xref target="RFC6377"/>).  As a result of this limited
		    utility of ADSP, it has not resulted in widespread
		    use.  Thus, although ADSP was discussed at length during
		    its development alongside DKIM, its was recently declared
		    Historic due to lack of uptake. </t>

		<t> There are new efforts within this space that are
		    encountering similar difficulties, although they have much
		    more industry support. </t>

		<t> The issues with mailing lists and similar re-mailing
		    applications could be resolved by a mechanism by which
		    the author domain ("A") can indicate that some other domain
		    ("B") is explicitly permitted to re-mail content generated
		    by "A", and receiver can observe signaling from both "A"
		    and "B" that this relationship exists. </t>

		<t> An experimental attempt to do so appeared in
		    <xref target="RFC6541"/>.  The method presented there
		    suffers from the burden on the author domain to publish
		    those relationships a prior via the DNS.  A mechanism that
		    does not have such an external dependency is
		    preferred. </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="defs" title="Definitions">
		<t> Numerous terms used here, especially "Author", are 
		    defined in <xref target="RFC5598"/>. </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="descr" title="DKIM-Delegate description">
		<t> "DKIM-Delegate" is a profile of DKIM that creates an
		    ephemeral relationship between a message author and
		    an intermediary that can be used by a receiver to
		    conclude that the intermediary legitimately handled
		    a message created by the author.  This makes it possible
		    to identify such messages separately from those without
		    such assurances, and thus the latter can be treated with
		    more skepticism. </t>

		<t> The specific mechanism is as follows:

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> The Author generates a message in the usual
			    way. </t>

			<t> The Author affixes a DKIM signature that
			    includes the entire message content in the body
			    hash.  (That is, it does not use the "l="
			    tag.) </t>

			<t> The Author affixes a second DKIM signature that
			    uses an "l=" tag to sign only a portion of the
			    message body, allowing content changes, 
			    and includes only a few key header fields
			    in the header hash.  The signature also has a short
			    expiration time, using an "x=" tag.  (See
			    <xref target="disc"/> for details.) </t>

			<t> The Author sends the message.  It may or may not
			    be handled by some intermediary agents before
			    arriving at the Recipient. </t>

			<t> The Recipient attempts to validate the first
			    DKIM signature affixed by the Author.  If it
			    is valid and not expired, the requirements of this
			    profile are satisfied (and the algorithm terminates
			    here). </t>

			<t> The Recipient attempts to validate the second
			    DKIM signature affixed by the Author.  If it
			    is not valid (or not found), the requirements
			    of this profile cannot be satisfied (and the
			    algorithm terminates here). </t>

			<t> The Recipient collects all header fields that
			    were covered by the header hash of the second
			    DKIM signature and that contain recipient
			    addresses.  These can be found in that
			    signature's "h=" tag.  The obvious examples are
			    the To and Cc fields (if present). </t>

			<t> The Recipient extracts the set of domain names
			    from the collected header fields.  Call this
			    set "D". </t>

			<t> The Recipient performs normal validation checks
			    of all other DKIM signatures on the message that
			    include the entire message body in their body
			    hashes, and stores the set of domains from passing
			    signatures in set "S". </t>

			<t> If the intersection of "D" and "S" is not empty,
			    the requirements of this profile are satisfied;
			    otherwise, the requirements are not satisfied. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="disc" title="Discussion">
		<t> The use of the first Author signature ensures
		    that if the original message arrives intact, the
		    Receiver is assured of its legitimacy as having been
		    generated and sent by the Author irrespective of what
		    intermediate agents handled it. </t>

		<t> Mailing list software commonly makes adjustments to a
		    message prior to sending it to subscribers, such as
		    prepending list-identifying material to the Subject
		    field, or appending URIs and such to the message body
		    referring Receivers to further information about the list
		    itself.  This will almost always invalidate the first
		    Author signature, so downstream receivers cannot be sure
		    (via DKIM, at least) where the message originated. </t>

		<t> The second "delegation" signature always covers the
		    visible recipient fields of the message, but typically
		    does not cover any of the content.  Under this profile,
		    domains that appear in those fields are permitted to alter
		    and re-send the content so long as they also sign (and thus
		    take responsibility for) the message thus generated. </t>

		<t> The delegation signature typically covers only the
		    following header fields:
			<list style="symbols">
				<t> From (required by DKIM) </t>

				<t> To and Cc (contain Receiver addresses) </t>

				<t> Message-Id (binds the signature to a
				    specific message) </t>

				<t> Date (binds the signature to a specific
				    date) </t>
			</list> </t>

		<t> Subject, though normally covered by signatures as per
		    Section 5.4 of <xref target="RFC6376"/>, can be omitted
		    for a delegation signature if the Author anticipates
		    legitimate alteration of it by a Mediator.  See also
		    <xref target="disc_header">. </t>

		<t> Similarly, the delegation signature typically covers the
		    message content, but allows for legitimate Mediator
		    modifications, by including an "l=" tag in the
		    signature. </t>

		<t> The expiration time on the second Author signature
		    selected needs to be long enough to permit evaluation by
		    recipients of the re-distribution of the message.  A good
		    choice is a small number of days or even hours. </t>

		<t> The profile assumes messages sent to the list that are not
		    part of a multipart message structure, as described in
		    Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (MIME; see
		    <xref target="RFC2045"/>).  It may not be possible to
		    select a practical signing length for messages in other
		    formats. </t>

		<t> The delegation signature can use an "l=" value reflecting
		    the entire message as generated by the Author, or "0"
		    allowing a complete reformatting of the message. 
		    Obviously the latter grants the modifying agent
		    considerable latitude in what it will ultimately emit,
		    while the former is much more constrained.  The Author
		    signing the message can choose whichever is more
		    appropriate for its own policies and requirements. </t>

		<section anchor="disc_header" title="Detecting Header Changes">
			<t> During the development of DKIM, consideration was
			    given to the notion of using the "z=" tag (if
			    present) to identify changes to the header made
			    in transit that render a signature invalid.
			    Ultimately it was decided that a signature should
			    be considered invalid even if analysis of the
			    content of "z=" could be used to confirm that the
			    change made in transit was innocuous.  The
			    content of "z=" was meant to be used only as a
			    debugging tool by humans. </t>

			<t> Under this profile, if the Subject header field
			    was included in the header hash, it may be useful
			    to use "z=" (if present) to detect changes made
			    to the Subject field, if any.  If those changes
			    appear to be trivial, such as the insertion of a
			    prefix string at the front of the header field's
			    original value, the Author and/or delegation
			    signature could be re-attempted with the original
			    Subject field value.  If the re-attempt succeeds,
			    the verifier could decide that this profile's
			    requirements have been satisfied. </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="tbd" title="Issues TBD">
		<t> <list style="symbols">
			<t> Should we create a new DKIM signature tag that
			    allows the Author to indicate in the delegation
			    signature a set of authorized re-signing domains
			    in addition to or other than the ones
			    implicit in "To" and "Cc"? </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
		<t> Use of this profile of DKIM amounts to an ephemeral
		    granting of the ability for the first Receivers (the
		    Mediators named in the To and Cc fields) to generate
		    content that the ultimate Receivers will consider valid
		    on behalf of the Author.  A compromised Mediator can
		    thus replace the original content in its entirety while
		    still satisfying this profile. </t>

		<t> Section 8.2 <xref target="RFC6376"/> discusses the
		    risks of using "l=" tags when generating signatures. 
		    The "l=" tag and its implications were discussed at length
		    during the development of DKIM, and its use today is not
		    popular because it opens up the possibility of replay-type
		    exploits where legitimate, signed messages are co-opted,
		    modified, and then sent as spam. </t>

		<t> Its use here is advocated only for the specific use cases
		    this document seeks to address, namely survivability of
		    Author signatures through modifying agents such as lists.
		    It is believed that the exposure thus created is tolerable,
		    in particular because a second signature without "l=" is
		    required for this profile to be satisfied, and the
		    exposure created by use of "l=" is constrained by a short
		    signature expiration time. </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
		<t> This document contains no actions for IANA. </t>

		<t> [RFC Editor: Please remove this section prior to
		    publication.] </t>
	</section>
</middle>

<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
		&RFC6376;
	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">
		&RFC5598;
		&RFC5617;
		&RFC6377;
		&RFC6541;
	</references>

	<section anchor="thanks" title="Acknowledgments">
		<t> The authors wish to acknowledge
		    Barry Leiba,
		    (other names)
		    and
		    (other name)
		    for their comments during the development of this
		    document. </t>
	</section>
</back>

</rfc>
