<?xml version="1.0" encoding="us-ascii"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC3777 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3777.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC3797 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3797.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC4071 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4071.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="bcp" obsoletes="3777, 5078, 5633, 5680, 6859"
        docName="draft-kucherawy-rfc3777bis-03">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc strict="no" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<front>
	<title abbrev="NomCom">
		IAB, IESG, and IAOC Selection, Confirmation, and Recall
		Process: Operation of the Nominating and Recall Committees
	</title>

	<author initials="M. S." surname="Kucherawy"
	        fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy"
		role="editor">

		<organization/> 

		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>270 Upland Drive</street>
				<city>San Francisco</city>
				<region>CA</region>
				<code>94127</code>
				<country>USA</country>
			</postal>

			<email>superuser@gmail.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>

	<date year="2014"/>

	<area>General</area>

	<abstract>
		<t> The process by which the members of the IAB and IESG,
		    and some members of the IAOC, are selected, confirmed, and
		    recalled is specified in this document.  This document
		    is a self-consistent, organized compilation of the process
		    as it was known at the time of publication of
		    <xref target="RFC3777"/>, with various updates since that
		    version was published. </t>
	</abstract>

</front>

<middle>
	<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
		<t> This document is a revision of and supercedes
		    BCP 10.  It is in essence a republishing of
		    <xref target="RFC3777"/> and the other RFCs that updated
		    that document into a single specification.  The result is
		    a complete specification of the process by which members
		    of the IAB and IESG, and some members of the IAOC, are
		    selected, confirmed, and recalled as of the date of its
		    approval. </t>

		<t> Section 4 of <xref target="RFC4071"/> provides further
		    details about the IAOC positions that are filled by
		    the nominating committee. </t>

		<t> The following two assumptions continue to be true of this
		    specification:

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> The Internet Research Task Force (IRTF) and
			    Internet Research Steering Group (IRSG) are not a
			    part of the process described here. </t>

			<t> The organization (and re-organization) of the IESG
			    is not a part of the process described here. </t>
		    </list> </t>

		<t> The time frames specified here use IETF meetings as
		    a frame of reference.  The time frames assume that the
		    IETF meets three times per calendar year with
		    approximately equal amounts of time between them.  The
		    meetings are referred to as the First IETF, Second IETF,
		    or Third IETF as needed. </t>

		<t> The next section lists the words and phrases commonly used
		    throughout this document with their intended meaning. </t>

		<t> The majority of this document is divided into four major
		    topics as follows:

		    <list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="General:"> This a set of rules and
				constraints that apply to the selection and
				confirmation process as a whole. </t>

			<t hangText="Nominating Committee Selection:"> This
				is the process by which the volunteers who
				will serve on the committee are
				selected. </t>

			<t hangText="Nominating Committee Operation:"> This
				is the set of principles, rules, and
				constraints that guide the activities of
				the nominating committee, including the
				confirmation process. </t>

			<t hangText="Member Recall:"> This is the process by
				which the behavior of a sitting member of the
				IAOC, IESG, or IAB may be questioned, perhaps
				resulting in the removal of the sitting
				member. </t>
		    </list> </t>

		<t> A final section describes how this document differs from
		    its predecessor <xref target="RFC3777"/>. </t>

		<t> An appendix of useful facts and practices collected from
		    previous nominating committees is also included. </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="defs" title="Definitions">
		<t> The following words and phrases are commonly used
		    throughout this document.  They are listed here with
		    their intended meaning for the convenience of the
		    reader.

		    <list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="candidate:"> A nominee who has been
				selected to be considered for confirmation by
				a confirming body. </t>

			<t hangText="confirmed candidate:"> A candidate that
				has been reviewed and approved by a
				confirming body. </t>

			<t hangText="nominating committee term:"> The term
				begins when its members are officially
				announced, which is expected to be prior to
				the Third IETF to ensure it is fully
				operational at the Third IETF.  The term ends
				at the Third IETF (not three meetings) after
				the next nominating committee's term
				begins. </t>

			<t hangText="nominee:"> A person who is being or has
				been considered for one or more open positions
				of the IESG, IAB, or IAOC. </t>

			<t hangText="sitting member:"> A person who is
				currently serving a term of membership in the
				IESG, IAB, or ISOC Board of Trustees. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="general" title="General">
		<t> The following set of rules apply to the process as a
		    whole.  If necessary, a paragraph discussing the
		    interpretation of each rule is included. </t>

		<section anchor="gen_completion" title="Completion Due">
			<t> The completion of the annual process is due
			    within seven months. </t>

			<t> The completion of the annual process is due
			    one month prior to the Friday of the week
			    before the First IETF.  It is expected to begin
			    at least eight months prior to the Friday of the
			    week before the First IETF. </t>

			<t> The process officially begins with the
			    announcement of the Chair of the committee.
			    The process officially ends when all confirmed
			    candidates have been announced. </t>

			<t> The annual process is comprised of three major
			    components as follows:

			    <list style="numbers">
				<t> The selection and organization of the
				    nominating committee members. </t>

				<t> The selection of candidates by the
				    nominating committee. </t>

				<t> The confirmation of the candidates. </t>
			    </list> </t>

			<t> There is an additional month set aside between
			    when the annual process is expected to end and
			    the term of the new candidates is to begin.  This
			    time may be used during unusual circumstances to
			    extend the time allocated for any of the
			    components listed above. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_func"
		         title="Nominating Committee Principal Functions">
			<t> The principal functions of the nominating
			    committee are to review each open IESG, IAB, and
			    IAOC position and to nominate either its incumbent
			    or a superior candidate. </t>

			<t> Although there is no term limit for serving in
			    any IESG, IAB, or IAOC position, the nominating
			    committee may use length of service as one of its
			    criteria for evaluating an incumbent. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee does not select the
			    open positions to be reviewed; it is instructed
			    as to which positions to review. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee will be given the title
			    of the positions to be reviewed and a brief
			    summary of the desired expertise of the candidate
			    that is nominated to fill each position. </t>

			<t> Incumbents must notify the nominating committee
			    if they wish to be nominated. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee does not confirm its
			    candidates; it presents its candidates to the
			    appropriate confirming body as indicated
			    below. </t>

			<t> A superior candidate is one who the nominating
			    committee believes would contribute in such a
			    way as to improve or enhance the body to which
			    he or she is nominated. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_positions"
		         title="Positions To Be Reviewed">
			<t> Approximately one-half of each of the then current
			    IESG and IAB positions, and one IAOC position, is
			    selected to be reviewed each year. </t>

			<t> The intent of this rule to ensure the review of
			    approximately one-half of each of the IESG and IAB
			    sitting members, and one of the two nominated
			    IAOC positions, each year.  It is recognized that
			    circumstances may exist that will require the
			    nominating committee to review more or less than
			    the usual number of positions, e.g., if the
			    IESG, IAB, or IAOC have re-organized prior to this
			    process and created new positions, if there are
			    an odd number of current positions, or if a member
			    unexpectedly resigns. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_terms" title="Term Lengths">
			<t> Confirmed candidates are expected to serve at
			    least a two year term. </t>

			<t> The intent of this rule is to ensure that members
			    of the IESG, IAB, and IAOC serve the number of
			    years that best facilitates the review of
			    one-half of the members each year. </t>

			<t> The term of a confirmed candidate selected
			    according to the mid-term vacancy rules may be
			    less than two years, as stated elsewhere in this
			    document. </t>

			<t> It is consistent with this rule for the nominating
			    committee to choose one or more of the currently
			    open positions to which it may assign a term of
			    not more than three years in order to ensure the
			    ideal application of this rule in the future. </t>

			<t> It is consistent with this rule for the nominating
			    committee to choose one or more of the currently
			    open positions that share responsibilities with
			    other positions (both those being reviewed and
			    those sitting) to which it may assign a term of
			    not more than three years to ensure that all such
			    members will not be reviewed at the same time. </t>

			<t> All sitting member terms end during the First IETF
			    meeting corresponding to the end of the term for
			    which they were confirmed.  All confirmed
			    candidate terms begin during the First IETF
			    meeting corresponding to the beginning of the term
			    for which they were confirmed. </t>

			<t> For confirmed candidates of the IESG the terms
			    begin no later than when the currently sitting
			    members' terms end on the last day of the meeting.
			    A term may begin or end no sooner than the first
			    day of the meeting and no later than the last day
			    of the meeting as determined by the mutual
			    agreement of the currently sitting member and the 
			    confirmed candidate.  A confirmed candidate's term
			    may overlap the sitting member's term during the
			    meeting as determined by their mutual
			    agreement. </t>

			<t> For confirmed candidates of the IAB and IAOC, the
			    terms overlap with the terms of the sitting
			    members for the entire week of the meeting. </t>

			<t> For candidates confirmed under the mid-term
			    vacancy rules, the term begins as soon as possible
			    after the confirmation. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_vacancies" title="Mid-Term Vacancies">
			<t> Mid-term vacancies are filled by the same rules
			    as documented here with four qualifications,
			    namely:

			    <list style="numbers">
				<t> When there is only one official nominating
				    committee, the body with the mid-term
				    vacancy relegates the responsibility to
				    fill the vacancy to it.  If the mid-term
				    vacancy occurs during the period of time
				    that the term of the prior year's
				    nominating committee overlaps with the
				    term of the current year's nominating
				    committee, the body with the mid-term
				    vacancy must relegate the responsibility
				    to fill the vacancy to the prior year's
				    nominating committee. </t>

				<t> If it is the case that the nominating
				    committee is reconvening to fill the
				    mid-term vacancy, then the completion of
				    the candidate selection and confirmation
				    process is due within six weeks, with all
				    other time periods otherwise unspecified
				    prorated accordingly. </t>

				<t> The confirming body has two weeks from the
				    day it is notified of a candidate to
				    reject the candidate, otherwise the
				    candidate is assumed to have been
				    confirmed. </t>

				<t> The term of the confirmed candidate will
				    be either:

				    <list style="letters">
					<t> the remainder of the term of the
					    open position if that remainder
					    is not less than one year; or </t>

					<t> the remainder of the term of the
					    open position plus the next two
					    year term if that remainder is
					    less than one year. </t>
				    </list> </t>
			        </list> </t>

			<t> In both cases a year is the period of time from a
			    First IETF meeting to the next First IETF
			    meeting. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_confidential" title="Confidentiality">
			<t> All deliberations and supporting information that
			    relates to specific nominees, candidates, and
			    confirmed candidates are confidential. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee and confirming body
			    members will be exposed to confidential
			    information as a result of their deliberations,
			    their interactions with those they consult, and
			    from those who provide requested supporting
			    information.  All members and all other
			    participants are expected to handle this
			    information in a manner consistent with its
			    sensitivity. </t>

			<t> It is consistent with this rule for current
			    nominating committee members who have served on
			    prior nominating committees to advise the current
			    committee on deliberations and results of the
			    prior committee, as necessary and appropriate. </t>

			<t> The list of nominees willing to be considered for
			    positions under review in the current nominating
			    committee cycle is not confidential.  The nominating
			    committee may disclose a list of names of nominees
			    who are willing to be considered for positions under
			    review to the community, in order to obtain feedback
			    from the community on these nominees. </t>

			<t> The list of nominees disclosed for a specific
			    position should contain only the names of nominees
			    who are willing to be considered for the position
			    under review. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee may choose not to include
			    some names in the disclosed list, at their
			    discretion. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee may disclose an updated
			    list, at its discretion.  For example, the
			    nominating committee might disclose an updated list
			    if it identifies errors/omissions in a previously
			    disclosed version of the disclosed list, or if the
			    nominating committee finds it necessary to call for
			    additional nominees, and these nominees indicate a
			    willingness to be considered before the nominating
			    committee has completed its deliberations. </t>

			<t> Nominees may choose to ask people to provide
			    feedback to the nominating committee, but should
			    not encourage any public statements of support.
			    Nominating committees should consider
			    nominee-encouraged lobbying and campaigning to be
			    unacceptable behavior. </t>

			<t> IETF community members are encouraged to provide
			    feedback on nominees to the nominating committee,
			    but should not post statements of support/non-support
			    for nominees in any public forum. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_model" title="Advice and Consent Model">
			<t> Unless otherwise specified, the advice and
			    consent model is used throughout the process.
			    This model is characterized as follows. </t>

			<section anchor="gen_model_1"
			         title="Positions To Be Reviewed">
				<t> The IETF Executive Director informs the
				    nominating committee of the IESG, IAB, and
				    IAOC positions to be reviewed. </t>

				<t> The IESG, IAB, and IAOC are responsible for
				    providing summary of the expertise desired
				    of the candidates selected for their
				    respective open positions to the Executive
				    Director.  The summaries are provided to
				    the nominating committee for its
				    consideration. </t>
			</section>

			<section anchor="gen_model_2"
			         title="Candidate Selection">
				<t> The nominating committee selects
				    candidates based on its understanding of
				    the IETF community's consensus of the
				    qualifications required and advises each
				    confirming body of its respective
				    candidates. </t>
			</section>

			<section anchor="gen_model_3" title="Candidate Review">
				<t> The confirming bodies review their
				    respective candidates, they may at their
				    discretion communicate with the nominating
				    committee, and then consent to some, all,
				    or none of the candidates. </t>

				<t> The sitting IAB members review the IESG
				    candidates. </t>

				<t> The Internet Society Board of Trustees
				    reviews the IAB candidates. </t>

				<t> The IAOC candidate is reviewed as
				    specified in <xref target="RFC4071"/>. </t>

				<t> The confirming bodies conduct their review
				    using all information and any means
				    acceptable to them, including but not
				    limited to the supporting information
				    provided by the nominating committee,
				    information known personally to members of
				    the confirming bodies and shared within
				    the confirming body, the results of
				    interactions within the confirming bodies,
				    and the confirming bodies interpretation
				    of what is in the best interests of the
				    IETF community. </t>

				<t> If all of the candidates are confirmed,
				    the job of the nominating committee with
				    respect to those open positions is
				    complete. </t>

				<t> If some or none of the candidates
				    submitted to a confirming body are
				    confirmed, the confirming body should
				    communicate with the nominating committee
				    both to explain the reason why all the
				    candidates were not confirmed and to
				    understand the nominating committee's
				    rationale for its candidates. </t>

				<t> The confirming body may reject individual
				    candidates, in which case the nominating
				    committee must select alternate candidates
				    for the rejected candidates. </t>

				<t> Any additional time required by the
				    nominating committee should not exceed its
				    maximum time allotment. </t>
			</section>

			<section anchor="gen_model_4" title="Confirmation">
				<t> A confirming body decides whether it
				    confirms each candidate using a
				    confirmation decision rule chosen by the
				    confirming body. </t>

				<t> If a confirming body has no specific
				    confirmation decision rule, then
				    confirming a given candidate should
				    require at least one-half of the
				    confirming body's sitting members to
				    agree to that confirmation. </t>

				<t> The decision may be made by conducting a
				    formal vote, by asserting consensus based
				    on informal exchanges (e.g., email), or
				    by any other mechanism that is used to
				    conduct the normal business of the
				    confirming body. </t>

				<t> Regardless of which decision rule the
				    confirming body uses, any candidate that
				    is not confirmed under that rule is
				    considered to be rejected. </t>

				<t> The confirming body must make its decision
				    within a reasonable time frame.  The
				    results from the confirming body must be
				    reported promptly to the nominating
				    committee. </t>
			</section>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_sitting" title="Sitting Members">
			<t> The following rules apply to nominees candidates
			    who are currently sitting members of the IESG, IAB,
			    or IAOC, and who are not sitting in an open
			    position being filled by the nominating
			    committee. </t>

			<t> The confirmation of a candidate to an open
			    position does not automatically create a vacancy
			    in the IESG, IAB, or IAOC position currently
			    occupied by the candidate.  The mid-term vacancy
			    can not exist until, first, the candidate formally
			    resigns from the current position and, second, the
			    body with the vacancy formally decides for itself
			    that it wants the nominating committee to fill the
			    mid-term vacancy according to the rules for a
			    mid-term vacancy documented elsewhere in this
			    document. </t>

			<t> The resignation should be effective as of when
			    the term of the new position begins.  The
			    resignation may remain confidential to the IAB,
			    IAOC, IESG, and nominating committee until the
			    confirmed candidate is announced for the new
			    position.  The process, according to rules set out
			    elsewhere in this document, of filling the seat
			    vacated by the confirmed candidate may begin as
			    soon as the vacancy is publicly announced. </t>

			<t> Filling a mid-term vacancy is a separate and
			    independent action from the customary action of
			    filling open positions.  In particular, a
			    nominating committee must complete its job with
			    respect to filling the open positions and then
			    separately proceed with the task of filling the
			    mid-term vacancy according to the rules for a
			    mid-term vacancy documented elsewhere in this
			    document. </t>

			<t> However, the following exception is permitted in
			    the case where the candidate for an open position
			    is currently a sitting member of the IAB.  It is
			    consistent with these rules for the announcements
			    of a resignation of a sitting member of the IAB
			    and of the confirmed candidate for the mid-term
			    vacancy created by that sitting member on the IAB
			    to all occur at the same time as long as the
			    actual sequence of events that occurred did so in
			    the following order:

			    <list style="numbers">
				<t> The nominating committee completes the
				    advice and consent process for the open
				    position being filled by the candidate
				    currently sitting on the IAB. </t>

				<t> The newly confirmed candidate resigns
				    from their current position on the
				    IAB. </t>

				<t> The IAB with the new mid-term vacancy
				    requests that the nominating committee
				    fill the position. </t>

				<t> The Executive Director of the IETF
				    informs the nominating committee of the
				    mid-term vacancy. </t>

				<t> The nominating committee acts on the
				    request to fill the mid-term vacancy. </t>
			    </list> </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="gen_announce" title="Announcements">
			<t> All announcements must be made using at least
			    the mechanism used by the IETF Secretariat for
			    its announcements, including a notice on the
			    IETF web site. </t>

			<t> As of the publication of this document, the
			    current mechanism is an email message to both
			    the "ietf" and the "ietf-announce" mailing
			    lists. </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="selection" title="Nominating Committee Selection">
		<t> The following set of rules apply to the creation of the
		    nominating committee and the selection of its members. </t>

		<section anchor="sel_timeline" title="Timeline">
			<t> The completion of the process of selecting and
			    organizing the members of the nominating committee
			    is due within three months. </t>

			<t> The completion of the selection and organization
			    process is due at least one month prior to the
			    Third IETF.  This ensures the nominating committee
			    is fully operational and available for interviews
			    and consultation during the Third IETF. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_term" title="Term">
			<t> The term of a nominating committee is expected to
			    be 15 months. </t>

			<t> It is the intent of this rule that the end of a
			    nominating committee's term overlap by
			    approximately three months the beginning of the
			    term of the next nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The term of a nominating committee begins when its
			    members are officially announced.  The term ends
			    at the Third IETF (not three meetings), i.e., the
			    IETF meeting after the next nominating committee's
			    term begins. </t>

			<t> A term is expected to begin at least two months
			    prior to the Third IETF to ensure the nominating
			    committee has at least one month to get organized
			    before preparing for the Third IETF. </t>

			<t> A nominating committee is expected to complete
			    any work-in-progress before it is dissolved at
			    the end of its term. </t>

			<t> During the period of time that the terms of the
			    nominating committees overlap, all mid-term
			    vacancies are to be relegated to the prior year's
			    nominating committee.  The prior year's nominating
			    committee has no other responsibilities during the
			    overlap period.  At all times other than the
			    overlap period there is exactly one official
			    nominating committee and it is responsible for
			    all mid-term vacancies. </t>

			<t> When the prior year's nominating committee is
			    filling a mid-term vacancy during the period of
			    time that the terms overlap, the nominating
			    committees operate independently.  However, some
			    coordination is needed between them.  Since the
			    prior year's Chair is a non-voting advisor to the
			    current nominating committee the coordination is
			    expected to be straightforward. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_structure" title="Structure">
			<t> The nominating committee comprises at least a
			    Chair, 10 voting volunteers, at least two liaisons,
			    and an advisor. </t>

			<t> Any committee member may propose the addition of
			    an advisor to participate in some or all of the
			    deliberations of the committee.  The addition
			    must be approved by the committee according to
			    its established voting mechanism.  Advisors
			    participate as individuals. </t>

			<t> Any committee member may propose the addition of a
			    liaison from other unrepresented organizations to
			    participate in some or all of the deliberations of
			    the committee.  The addition must be approved by
			    the committee according to its established voting
			    mechanism.  Liaisons participate as
			    representatives of their respective
			    organizations. </t>

			<t> The Chair is selected according to rules stated
			    elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> The 10 voting volunteers are selected according
			    to rules stated elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> The IESG and IAB liaisons are selected
			    according to rules stated elsewhere in this
			    document. </t>

			<t> The Internet Society Board of Trustees may appoint
			    a liaison to the nominating committee at its own
			    discretion. </t>

			<t> The Chair of last year's nominating committee
			    serves as an advisor according to rules stated
			    elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> None of the Chair, liaisons, or advisors vote on
			    the selection of candidates.  They do vote on all
			    other issues before the committee unless otherwise
			    specified in this document. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_chair_duties" title="Chair Duties">
			<t> The Chair of the nominating committee is
			    responsible for ensuring the nominating committee
			    completes its assigned duties in a timely fashion
			    and performs in the best interests of the IETF
			    community. </t>

			<t> The Chair must be thoroughly familiar with the
			    rules and guidance indicated throughout this
			    document.  The Chair must ensure the nominating
			    committee completes its assigned duties in a
			    manner that is consistent with this document. </t>

			<t> The Chair must attest by proclamation at a plenary
			    session of the First IETF that the results of
			    the committee represent its best effort and the
			    best interests of the IETF community. </t>

			<t> The Chair does not vote on the selection of
			    candidates. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_chair_selection" title="Chair Selection">
			<t> The Internet Society President appoints the
			    Chair, who must meet the same requirements for
			    membership in the nominating committee as a
			    voting volunteer. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee Chair must agree to
			    invest the time necessary to ensure that the
			    nominating committee completes its assigned duties
			    and to perform in the best interests of the
			    IETF community in that role. </t>

			<t> The appointment is due no later than the Second
			    IETF meeting to ensure it can be announced during
			    a plenary session at that meeting.  The completion
			    of the appointment is necessary to ensure the
			    annual process can complete at the time specified
			    elsewhere in this document. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_chair_temp" title="Temporary Chair">
			<t> A Chair, in consultation with the Internet
			    Society President, may appoint a temporary
			    substitute for the Chair position. </t>

			<t> There are a variety of ordinary circumstances
			    that may arise from time to time that could
			    result in a Chair being unavailable to oversee
			    the activities of the committee.  The Chair, in
			    consultation with the Internet Society President,
			    may appoint a substitute from a pool comprised of
			    the liaisons currently serving on the committee
			    and the prior year's Chair or designee. </t>

			<t> Any such appointment must be temporary and does
			    not absolve the Chair of any or all responsibility
			    for ensuring the nominating committee completes
			    its assigned duties in a timely fashion. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_liaisons_1" title="Liaisons">
			<t> Liaisons are responsible for ensuring the
			    nominating committee in general and the Chair in
			    particular execute their assigned duties in the
			    best interests of the IETF community. </t>

			<t> Liaisons are expected to represent the views of
			    their respective organizations during the
			    deliberations of the committee.  They should
			    provide information as requested or when they
			    believe it would be helpful to the committee. </t>

			<t> Liaisons from the IESG and IAB are expected
			    to provide information to the nominating committee
			    regarding the operation, responsibility, and
			    composition of their respective bodies. </t>

			<t> Liaisons are expected to convey questions from the
			    committee to their respective organizations and
			    responses to those questions to the committee, as
			    requested by the committee. </t>

			<t> Liaisons from the IESG, IAB, and Internet
			    Society Board of Trustees (if one was appointed)
			    are expected to review the operation and executing
			    process of the nominating committee and to report
			    any concerns or issues to the Chair of the
			    nominating committee immediately.  If they can not
			    resolve the issue between themselves, liaisons must
			    report it according to the dispute resolution
			    process stated elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> Liaisons from confirming bodies are expected to
			    assist the committee in preparing the testimony it
			    is required to provide with its candidates. </t>

			<t> Liaisons may have other nominating committee
			    responsibilities as required by their respective
			    organizations or requested by the nominating
			    committee, except that such responsibilities may
			    not conflict with any other provisions of this
			    document. </t>

			<t> Liaisons do not vote on the selection of
			    candidates. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_liaisons_2" title="Liaison Appointment">
			<t> The sitting IAB and IESG members each
			    appoint a liaison from their current membership,
			    someone who is not sitting in an open position, to
			    serve on the nominating committee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_advisors" title="Advisors">
			<t> An advisor is responsible for such duties as
			    specified by the invitation that resulted in
			    the appointment. </t>

			<t> Advisors do not vote on the selection of
			    candidates. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_chair_past" title="Past Chair">
			<t> The Chair of the prior year's nominating committee
			    serves as an advisor to the current committee. </t>

			<t> The prior year's Chair is expected to review the
			    actions and activities of the current Chair and to
			    report any concerns or issues to the nominating
			    committee Chair immediately.  If they can not
			    resolve the issue between themselves, the prior
			    year's Chair must report it according to the
			    dispute resolution process stated elsewhere in this
			    document. </t>

			<t> The prior year's Chair may select a designee from
			    a pool composed of the voting volunteers of the
			    prior year's committee and all prior Chairs if the
			    Chair is unavailable.  If the prior year's Chair is
			    unavailable or is unable or unwilling to make such a
			    designation in a timely fashion, the Chair of the
			    current year's committee may select a designee in
			    consultation with the Internet Society
			    President. </t>

			<t> Selecting a prior year's committee member as the
			    designee permits the experience of the prior year's
			    deliberations to be readily available to the current
			    committee.  Selecting an earlier prior year Chair
			    as the designee permits the experience of being a
			    Chair as well as that Chair's committee
			    deliberations to be readily available to the current
			    committee. </t>

			<t> All references to "prior year's Chair" in this
			    document refer to the person serving in that role,
			    whether it is the actual prior year's Chair or a
			    designee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_volunteers" title="Voting Volunteers">
			<t> Voting volunteers are responsible for completing the
			    tasks of the nominating committee in a timely
			    fashion. </t>

			<t> Each voting volunteer is expected to participate in
			    all activities of the nominating committee with a
			    level of effort approximately equal to all other
			    voting volunteers.  Specific tasks to be completed
			    are established and managed by the Chair according
			    to rules stated elsewhere in this document. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_milestones" title="Milestones">
			<t> The Chair must establish and announce milestones for
			    the selection of the nominating committee
			    members. </t>

			<t> There is a defined time period during which the
			    selection process is due to be completed.  The
			    Chair must establish a set of milestones which,
			    if met in a timely fashion, will result in the
			    completion of the process on time. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_positions" title="Open Positions">
			<t> The Chair (or the IETF Executive Director, if no
			    Chair has been named four weeks after the first IETF
			    meeting of the year) obtains the list of positions
			    to be reviewed and announces it along with a
			    solicitation for names of volunteers from the IETF
			    community willing to serve on the nominating
			    committee. </t>

			<t> If the IETF Executive Director issues the
			    solicitation for volunteers, the IETF Executive
			    Director must also collect responses to the
			    solicitation and provide the names of volunteers to
			    the incoming nominating committee Chair when the
			    incoming nominating committee Chair is named. </t>

			<t> At the Chair's request, the IETF Secretariat may
			    perform other clerical support tasks, as long as
			    the task being performed does not require nominating
			    committee Chair judgment, in the nominating
			    committee Chair's opinion, and as long as the
			    community is appropriately notified that this
			    request is being made.  This request may come from
			    the incoming nominating committee Chair (if one has
			    been selected for this nominating committee cycle)
			    or the previous nominating committee Chair (if the
			    search for an incoming nominating committee Chair is
			    still underway). </t>

			<t> The solicitation must permit the community at
			    least 30 days during which they may choose to
			    volunteer to be selected for the nominating
			    committee. </t>

			<t> The list of open positions is published with the
			    solicitation to facilitate community members
			    choosing between volunteering for an open position
			    and volunteering for the nominating committee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_qualify" title="Volunteer Qualification">
			<t> Members of the IETF community must have attended at
			    least three of the last five IETF meetings in order
			    to volunteer. </t>

			<t> The five meetings are the five most recent meetings
			    that ended prior to the date on which the
			    solicitation for nominating committee volunteers
			    was submitted for distribution to the IETF
			    community. </t>

			<t> The IETF Secretariat is responsible for confirming
			    that volunteers have met the attendance
			    requirement. </t>

			<t> Volunteers must provide their full name, email
			    address, and primary company or organization
			    affiliation (if any) when volunteering. </t>

			<t> Volunteers are expected to be familiar with the
			    IETF processes and procedures, which are readily
			    learned by active participation in a working group
			    and especially by serving as a document editor
			    or working group chair. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_disqualify" title="Not Qualified">
			<t> Any person who serves on any of the Internet
			    Society Board of Trustees, the IAB, the IESG, or
			    the IAOC, including those who serve on these bodies
			    in ex officio positions, may not volunteer to serve
			    as voting members of the nominating committee.
			    Liaisons to these bodies from other bodies or
			    organizations are not excluded by this rule. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_process" title="Selection Process">
			<t> The Chair announces both the list of the pool
			    of volunteers from which the 10 voting volunteers
			    will be randomly selected and the method with which
			    the selection will be completed. </t>

  			<t> The announcement should be made at least one week
			    prior to the date on which the random selection will
			    occur.  </t>

			<t> The pool of volunteers must be enumerated or
			    otherwise indicated according to the needs of the
			    selection method to be used. </t>

			<t> The announcement must specify the data that will be
			    used as input to the selection method.  The method
			    must depend on random data whose value is not
			    known or available until the date on which the
			    random selection will occur. </t>

			<t> It must be possible to independently verify that
			    the selection method used is both fair and
			    unbiased.  A method is fair if each eligible
			    volunteer is equally likely to be selected.  A
			    method is unbiased if no one can influence its
			    outcome in favor of a specific outcome. </t>

			<t> It must be possible to repeat the selection method,
			    either through iteration or by restarting in such a
			    way as to remain fair and unbiased.  This is
			    necessary to replace selected volunteers should they
			    become unavailable after selection. </t>

			<t> The selection method must produce an ordered list
			    of volunteers. </t>

			<t> One possible selection method is described in
			    <xref target="RFC3797"/>. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_announce"
		         title="Announcement of Selection Results">
			<t> The Chair randomly selects the 10 voting
			    volunteers from the pool of names of volunteers and
			    announces the members of the nominating
			    committee. </t>

			<t> No more than two volunteers with the same primary
			    affiliation may be selected for the nominating
			    committee.  The Chair reviews the primary
			    affiliation of each volunteer selected by the
			    method in turn.  If the primary affiliation for a
			    volunteer is the same as two previously selected
			    volunteers, that volunteer is removed from
			    consideration and the method is repeated to identify
			    the next eligible volunteer. </t>

			<t> There must be at least two announcements of all
			    members of the nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The first announcement should occur as soon after
			    the random selection as is reasonable for the
			    Chair.  The community must have at least one week
			    during which any member may challenge the results of
			    the random selection. </t>

			<t> The challenge must be made in writing (email is
			    acceptable) to the Chair.  The Chair has 48 hours to
			    review the challenge and offer a resolution to the
			    member.  If the resolution is not accepted by the
			    member, that member may report the challenge
			    according to the dispute resolution process stated
			    elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> If a selected volunteer, upon reading the
			    announcement with the list of selected volunteers,
			    finds that two or more other volunteers have the
			    same affiliation, then the volunteer should notify
			    the Chair who will determine the appropriate
			    action. </t>

			<t> During at least the one week challenge period the
			    Chair must contact each of the members and confirm
			    their willingness and availability to serve.  The
			    Chair should make every reasonable effort to contact
			    each member.

			    <list style="symbols">
				<t> If the Chair is unable to contact a liaison
				    the problem is referred to the respective
				    organization to resolve.  The Chair should
				    allow a reasonable amount of time for the
				    organization to resolve the problem and then
				    may proceed without the liaison. </t>

				<t> If the Chair is unable to contact an advisor
				    the Chair may elect to proceed without the
				    advisor, except for the prior year's Chair
				    for whom the Chair must consult with the
				    Internet Society President as stated
				    elsewhere in this document. </t>

				<t> If the Chair is unable to contact a voting
				    volunteer the Chair must repeat the random
				    selection process in order to replace the
				    unavailable volunteer.  There should be at
				    least one day between the announcement of
				    the iteration and the selection process. </t>
			    </list> </t>

			<t> After at least one week and confirming that 10
			    voting volunteers are ready to serve, the Chair
			    makes the second announcement of the members of the
			    nominating committee, which officially begins the
			    term of the nominating committee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="sel_organize"
		         title="Committee Organization">
			<t> The Chair works with the members of the committee to
			    organize itself in preparation for completing its
			    assigned duties. </t>

			<t> The committee has approximately one month during
			    which it can self-organize.  Its responsibilities
			    during this time include but are not limited to the
			    following:

			    <list style="symbols">
				<t> Setting up a regular teleconference
				    schedule. </t>

				<t> Setting up an internal web site. </t>

				<t> Setting up a mailing list for internal
				    discussions. </t>

				<t> Setting up an email address for receiving
				    community input. </t>

				<t> Establishing operational procedures. </t>

				<t> Establishing milestones in order to monitor
				    the progress of the selection process. </t>
			    </list> </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="operation" title="Nominating Committee Operation">
		<t> The following rules apply to the operation of the
		    nominating committee.  If necessary, a paragraph
		    discussing the interpretation of each rule is
		    included. </t>

		<t> The rules are organized approximately in the order
		    in which they would be invoked. </t>

		<section anchor="op_discretion" title="Discretion">
			<t> All rules and special circumstances not otherwise
			    specified are at the discretion of the
			    committee. </t>

			<t> Exceptional circumstances will occasionally arise
			    during the normal operation of the nominating
			    committee.  This rule is intended to foster the
			    continued forward progress of the committee. </t>

			<t> Any member of the committee may propose a rule for
			    adoption by the committee.  The rule must be
			    approved by the committee according to its
			    established voting mechanism. </t>

			<t> All members of the committee should consider whether
			    the exception is worthy of mention in the next
			    revision of this document and follow-up
			    accordingly. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_timeline_1" title="Selection Timeline">
			<t> The completion of the process of selecting
			    candidates to be confirmed by their respective
			    confirming body is due within three months. </t>

			<t> The completion of the selection process is due at
			    least two month's prior to the First IETF.  This
			    ensures the nominating committee has sufficient time
			    to complete the confirmation process. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_timeline_2" title="Confirmation Timeline">
			<t> The completion of the process of confirming the
			    candidates is due within one month. </t>

			<t> The completion of the confirmation process is due
			    at least one month prior to the First IETF. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_milestones" title="Milestones">
			<t> The Chair must establish for the nominating
			    committee a set of milestones for the candidate
			    selection and confirmation process. </t>

			<t> There is a defined time period during which the
			    candidate selection and confirmation process must be
			    completed.  The Chair must establish a set of
			    milestones which, if met in a timely fashion, will
			    result in the completion of the process on time.
			    The Chair should allow time for iterating the
			    activities of the committee if one or more
			    candidates is not confirmed. </t>

			<t> The Chair should ensure that all committee members
			    are aware of the milestones. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_voting" title="Voting Mechanism">
			<t> The Chair must establish a voting mechanism. </t>

			<t> The committee must be able to objectively determine
			    when a decision has been made during its
			    deliberations.  The criteria for determining closure
			    must be established and known to all members of the
			    nominating committee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_quorum" title="Voting Quorum">
			<t> At least a quorum of committee members must
			    participate in a vote. </t>

			<t> Only voting volunteers vote on a candidate
			    selection.  For a candidate selection vote a
			    quorum is comprised of at least seven of the
			    voting volunteers. </t>

			<t> At all other times a quorum is present if at
			    least 75% of the nominating committee members are
			    participating. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_recall_1" title="Voting Member Recall">
			<t> Any member of the nominating committee may propose
			    to the committee that any other member except the
			    Chair be recalled.  The process for recalling the
			    Chair is defined elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> There are a variety of ordinary circumstances that
			    may arise that could result in one or more members
			    of the committee being unavailable to complete their
			    assigned duties, for example health concerns, family
			    issues, or a change of priorities at work.  A
			    committee member may choose to resign for
			    unspecified personal reasons.  In addition, the
			    committee may not function well as a group because
			    a member may be disruptive or otherwise
			    uncooperative. </t>

			<t> Regardless of the circumstances, if individual
			    committee members can not work out their differences
			    between themselves, the entire committee may be
			    called upon to discuss and review the
			    circumstances.  If a resolution is not forthcoming a
			    vote may be conducted.  A member may be recalled if
			    at least a quorum of all committee members agree,
			    including the vote of the member being recalled. </t>

			<t> If a liaison member is recalled the committee must
			    notify the affected organization and must allow a
			    reasonable amount of time for a replacement to be
			    identified by the organization before
			    proceeding. </t>

			<t> If an advisor member other than the prior year's
			    Chair is recalled, the committee may choose to
			    proceed without the advisor.  In the case of the
			    prior year's Chair, the Internet Society President
			    must be notified and the current Chair must be
			    allowed a reasonable amount of time to consult with
			    the Internet Society President to identify a
			    replacement before proceeding. </t>

			<t> If a single voting volunteer position on the
			    nominating committee is vacated, regardless of the
			    circumstances, the committee may choose to proceed
			    with only nine voting volunteers at its own
			    discretion.  In all other cases a new voting member
			    must be selected, and the Chair must repeat the
			    random selection process including an announcement
			    of the iteration prior to the actual selection as
			    stated elsewhere in this document. </t>

			<t> A change in the primary affiliation of a voting
			    volunteer during the term of the nominating
			    committee is not a cause to request the recall of
			    that volunteer, even if the change would result in
			    more than two voting volunteers with the same
			    affiliation. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_recall_2" title="Chair Recall">
			<t> Only the prior year's Chair may request the
			    recall of the current Chair. </t>

			<t> It is the responsibility of the prior year's
			    Chair to ensure the current Chair completes the
			    assigned tasks in a manner consistent with this
			    document and in the best interests of the IETF
			    community. </t>

			<t> Any member of the committee who has an issue or
			    concern regarding the Chair should report it to
			    the prior year's Chair immediately.  The prior
			    year's Chair is expected to report it to the Chair
			    immediately.  If they can not resolve the issue
			    between themselves, the prior year's Chair must
			    report it according to the dispute resolution
			    process stated elsewhere in this document. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_deliberations" title="Deliberations">
			<t> All members of the nominating committee may
			    participate in all deliberations. </t>

			<t> The emphasis of this rule is that no member can be
			    explicitly excluded from any deliberation.  However,
			    a member may individually choose not to participate
			    in a deliberation. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_call" title="Call for Nominees">
			<t> The Chair announces the open positions to be
			    reviewed, the desired expertise provided by the
			    IETF Executive Director, and the call for
			    nominees. </t>

			<t> The call for nominees must include a request for
			    comments regarding the past performance of
			    incumbents, which will be considered during the
			    deliberations of the nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The call must request that a nomination include a
			    valid, working email address, a telephone number,
			    or both for the nominee.  The nomination must
			    include the set of skills or expertise the nominator
			    believes the nominee has that would be
			    desirable. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_nominations" title="Nominations">
			<t> Any member of the IETF community may nominate any
			    member of the IETF community for any open position,
			    whose eligibility to serve will be confirmed by the
			    nominating committee. </t>

			<t> A self-nomination is permitted. </t>

			<t> Nominating committee members are not eligible to
			    be considered for filling any open position by
			    the nominating committee on which they serve.  They
			    become ineligible as soon as the term of the
			    nominating committee on which they serve officially
			    begins.  They remain ineligible for the duration of
			    that nominating committee's term. </t>

			<t> Although each nominating committee's term overlaps
			    with the following nominating committee's term,
			    nominating committee members are eligible for
			    nomination by the following committee if not
			    otherwise disqualified. </t>

			<t> Members of the IETF community who were recalled
			    from any IESG, IAB, or IAOC position during the
			    previous two years are not eligible to be
			    considered for filling any open position. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_candidates" title="Candidate Selection">
			<t> The nominating committee selects candidates based
			    on its understanding of the IETF community's
			    consensus of the qualifications required to fill
			    the open positions. </t>

			<t> The intent of this rule is to ensure that the
			    nominating committee consults with a broad base of
			    the IETF community for input to its deliberations.
			    In particular, the nominating committee must
			    determine if the desired expertise for the open
			    positions matches its understanding of the
			    qualifications desired by the IETF community. </t>

			<t> The consultations are permitted to include names
			    of nominees, if all parties to the consultation
			    agree to observe the same confidentiality rules as
			    the nominating committee itself, or the names are
			    public as discussed in
			    <xref target="gen_confidential"/>.  Feedback on
			    individual nominees should always be
			    confidential. </t>

			<t> A broad base of the community should include the
			    existing members of the IAB, IAOC, and IESG,
			    especially sitting members who share
			    responsibilities with open positions, e.g.,
			    co-Area Directors, and working group chairs,
			    especially those in the areas with open
			    positions. </t>

			<t> Only voting volunteer members vote to select
			    candidates. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_consent" title="Consent to Nomination">
			<t> Nominees should be advised that they are being
			    considered and must consent to their nomination
			    prior to being chosen as candidates. </t>

			<t> Although the nominating committee will make every
			    reasonable effort to contact and to remain in
			    contact with nominees, any nominee whose contact
			    information changes during the process and who
			    wishes to still be considered should inform the
			    nominating committee of the changes. </t>

			<t> A nominee's consent must be written (email is
			    acceptable) and must include a commitment to provide
			    the resources necessary to fill the open position
			    and an assurance that the nominee will perform the
			    duties of the position for which they are being
			    considered in the best interests of the IETF
			    community. </t>

			<t> Consenting to a nomination must occur prior to a
			    nominee being a candidate and may occur as soon
			    after the nomination as needed by the nominating
			    committee. </t>

			<t> Consenting to a nomination must not imply the
			    nominee will be a candidate. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee should help nominees
			    provide justification to their employers. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_announce_1"
		         title="Notifying Confirming Bodies">
			<t> The nominating committee advises the confirming
			    bodies of their candidates, specifying a single
			    candidate for each open position and testifying as
			    to how each candidate meets the qualifications of
			    an open position. </t>

			<t> For each candidate, the testimony must include a
			    brief statement of the qualifications for the
			    position that is being filled, which may be exactly
			    the expertise that was requested.  If the
			    qualifications differ from the expertise originally
			    requested a brief statement explaining the
			    difference must be included. </t>

			<t> The testimony may include either or both of a brief
			    resume of the candidate and a brief summary of the
			    deliberations of the nominating committee. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_announce_2" title="Confirming Candidates">
			<t> Confirmed candidates must consent to their
			    confirmation and rejected candidates and nominees
			    must be notified before confirmed candidates are
			    announced. </t>

			<t> It is not necessary to notify and get consent from
			    all confirmed candidates together. </t>

			<t> A nominee may not know they were a candidate.  This
			    permits a candidate to be rejected by a confirming
			    body without the nominee knowing about the
			    rejection. </t>

			<t> Rejected nominees, who consented to their
			    nomination, and rejected candidates must be notified
			    prior to announcing the confirmed candidates. </t>

			<t> It is not necessary to announce all confirmed
			    candidates together. </t>

			<t> The nominating committee must ensure that all
			    confirmed candidates are prepared to serve prior to
			    announcing their confirmation. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="op_archive" title="Archives">
			<t> The nominating committee should archive the
			    information it has collected or produced for a
			    period of time not to exceed its term. </t>

			<t> The purpose of the archive is to assist the
			    nominating committee should it be necessary for it
			    to fill a mid-term vacancy. </t>

			<t> The existence of an archive, how it is implemented,
			    and what information to archive is at the discretion
			    of the committee.  The decision must be approved by
			    a quorum of the voting volunteer members. </t>

			<t> The implementation of the archive should make every
			    reasonable effort to ensure that the confidentiality
			    of the information it contains is maintained. </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="dispute" title="Dispute Resolution Process">
		<t> The dispute resolution process described here is to be used
		    as indicated elsewhere in this document.  Its applicability
		    in other circumstances is beyond the scope of this
		    document. </t>

		<t> The nominating committee operates under a strict rule of
		    confidentiality.  For this reason when process issues arise
		    it is best to make every reasonable effort to resolve them
		    within the committee.  However, when circumstances do not
		    permit this or no resolution is forthcoming, the process
		    described here is to be used. </t>

		<t> The following rules apply to the process.

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> The results of this process are final and binding.
			    There is no appeal. </t>

			<t> The process begins with the submission of a request
			    as described below to the Internet Society
			    President. </t>

			<t> As soon as the process begins, the nominating
			    committee may continue those activities that are
			    unrelated to the issue to be resolved except that
			    it must not submit any candidates to a confirming
			    body until the issue is resolved. </t>

			<t> All parties to the process are subject to the
			    same confidentiality rules as each member of the
			    nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The process should be completed within two
			    weeks. </t>
		    </list> </t>

		<t> The process is as follows: 

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> The party seeking resolution submits a written
			    request (email is acceptable) to the Internet
			    Society President detailing the issue to be
			    resolved. </t>

			<t> The Internet Society President appoints an arbiter
			    to investigate and resolve the issue.  A
			    self-appointment is permitted. </t>

			<t> The arbiter investigates the issue making every
			    reasonable effort to understand both sides of the
			    issue.  Since the arbiter is subject to the same
			    confidentiality obligations as all nominating
			    committee members, all members are expected to
			    cooperate fully with the arbiter and to provide all
			    relevant information to the arbiter for review. </t>

			<t> After consultation with the two principal parties
			    to the issue, the arbiter decides on a resolution.
			    Whatever actions are necessary to execute the
			    resolution are immediately begun and completed as
			    quickly as possible. </t>

			<t> The arbiter summarizes the issue, the resolution,
			    and the rationale for the resolution for the
			    Internet Society President. </t>

			<t> In consultation with the Internet Society President,
			    the arbiter prepares a report of the dispute and
			    its resolution.  The report should include all
			    information that in the judgment of the arbiter
			    does not violate the confidentiality requirements
			    of the nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The Chair includes the dispute report when
			    reporting on the activities of the nominating
			    committee to the IETF community. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="recall" title="Member Recall">
		<t> The following rules apply to the recall process.  If
		    necessary, a paragraph discussing the interpretation of
		    each rule is included. </t>

		<section anchor="recall_petition" title="Petition">
			<t> At any time, at least 20 members of the IETF
			    community, who are qualified to be voting members
			    of a nominating committee, may request by signed
			    petition (email is acceptable) to the Internet
			    Society President the recall of any sitting IAB,
			    IAOC, or IESG member. </t>

			<t> All individual and collective qualifications of
			    nominating committee eligibility are applicable,
			    including that no more than two signatories may
			    have the same primary affiliation. </t>

			<t> Each signature must include a full name, email
			    address, and primary company or organization
			    affiliation. </t>

			<t> The IETF Secretariat is responsible for confirming
			    that each signatory is qualified to be a voting
			    member of a nominating committee.  A valid petition
			    must be signed by at least 20 qualified
			    signatories. </t>

			<t> The petition must include a statement of
			    justification for the recall and all relevant and
			    appropriate supporting documentation. </t>

			<t> The petition and its signatories must be announced
			    to the IETF community. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_chair" title="Recall Committee Chair">
			<t> Internet Society President shall appoint a Recall
			    Committee Chair. </t>

			<t> The Internet Society President must not evaluate the
			    recall request.  It is explicitly the responsibility
			    of the IETF community to evaluate the behavior of
			    its leaders. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_cmte" title="Recall Committee Creation">
			<t> The recall committee is created according to the
			    same rules as is the nominating committee with the
			    qualifications that both the person being
			    investigated and the parties requesting the recall
			    must not be a member of the recall committee in any
			    capacity. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_rules" title="Recall Committee Rules">
			<t> The recall committee operates according to the same
			    rules as the nominating committee with the
			    qualification that there is no confirmation
			    process. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_ops" title="Recall Committee Operation">
			<t> The recall committee investigates the circumstances
			    of the justification for the recall and votes on
			    its findings. </t>

			<t> The investigation must include at least both an
			    opportunity for the member being recalled to present
			    a written statement and consultation with third
			    parties. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_maj" title="3/4 Majority">
			<t> A 3/4 majority of the members who vote on the
			    question is required for a recall. </t>
		</section>

		<section anchor="recall_position" title="Position To Be Filled">
			<t> If a sitting member is recalled the open position is
			    to be filled according to the mid-term vacancy
			    rules. </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
		<t> This document contains no actions for IANA. </t>

		<t> [RFC Editor: Please remove this section prior to
		    publication.] </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
		<t> Any selection, confirmation, or recall process
		    necessarily involves investigation into the qualifications
		    and activities of prospective candidates.  The
		    investigation may reveal confidential or otherwise private
		    information about candidates to those participating in the
		    process.  Each person who participates in any aspect of
		    the process must maintain the confidentiality of any and
		    all information not explicitly identified as suitable for
		    public dissemination. </t>

		<t> When the nominating committee decides it is necessary to
		    share confidential or otherwise private information with
		    others, the dissemination must be minimal and must
		    include a prior commitment from all persons consulted to
		    observe the same confidentiality rules as the nominating
		    committee itself. </t>
	</section>
</middle>

<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
		&RFC3777;
		&RFC4071;
	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">
		&RFC3797;
	</references>

	<section anchor="changes" title="Changes Since RFC 3777">
		<t> <list style="symbols">
			<t> Converted from nroff to xml2rfc, resulting in
			    some reformatting. </t>

			<t> Applied RFC 3777 errata. </t>

			<t> Applied RFC 5078 update. </t>

			<t> Applied RFC 5633 update. </t>

			<t> Applied RFC 5680 update. </t>

			<t> Applied RFC 6859 update. </t>

			<t> Applied errata #232. </t>

			<t> Applied errata #4179. </t>

			<t> A few grammatical corrections. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="oral" title="Oral Tradition">
		<t> Over the years various nominating committees have learned
		    through oral tradition passed on by liaisons that there are
		    certain consistencies in the process and information
		    considered during deliberations.  Some items from that oral
		    tradition are collected here to facilitate its consideration
		    by future nominating committees.

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> It has been found that experience as an IETF
			    Working Group Chair or an IRTF Research Group Chair
			    is helpful in giving a nominee experience of what
			    the job of an Area Director involves.  It also
			    helps a nominating committee judge the technical,
			    people, and process management skills of the
			    nominee. </t>

			<t> No person should serve both on the IAB and as an
			    Area Director, except the IETF Chair whose roles as
			    an IAB member and Area Director of the General Area
			    are set out elsewhere. </t>

			<t> The strength of the IAB is found in part in the
			    balance of the demographics of its members (e.g.,
			    national distribution, years of experience, gender,
			    etc.), the combined skill set of its members, and
			    the combined sectors (e.g., industry, academia,
			    etc.) represented by its members. </t>

			<t> There are no term limits explicitly because the
			    issue of continuity versus turnover should be
			    evaluated each year according to the expectations of
			    the IETF community, as it is understood by each
			    nominating committee. </t>

			<t> The number of nominating committee members with the
			    same primary affiliation is limited in order to
			    avoid the appearance of improper bias in choosing
			    the leadership of the IETF.  Rather than defining
			    precise rules for how to define "affiliation", the
			    IETF community depends on the honor and integrity of
			    the participants to make the process work. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="timeline" title="Nominating Committee Timeline">
		<t> This appendix is included for the convenience of the reader
		    and is not to be interpreted as the definitive timeline.
		    It is intended to capture the detail described elsewhere in
		    this document in one place.  Although every effort has been
		    made to ensure the description here is consistent with the
		    description elsewhere, if there are any conflicts the
		    definitive rule is the one in the main body of this
		    document. </t>

		<t> The only absolute in the timeline rules for the annual
		    process is that its completion is due by the First IETF of
		    the year after the nominating committee begins its term.
		    This is supported by the fact that the confirmed candidate
		    terms begin during the week of the First IETF. </t>

		<t> The overall annual process is designed to be completed in
		    seven months.  It is expected to start nine months prior to
		    the First IETF.  The time is split between three
		    major components of the process roughly as follows:

		    <list style="numbers">
			<t> First is the selection and organization of the
			    committee members.  Three months are allotted for
			    this process. </t>

			<t> Second is the selection of the candidates by the
			    nominating committee.  Four months are allotted
			    for this process. </t>

			<t> Third is the confirmation of the candidates by
			    their respective confirming bodies.  Two months are
			    allotted for this process. </t>
		    </list> </t>

		<t> The following list captures the details of the milestones
		    within each component.  For illustrative purposes the
		    list presumes the Friday before the First IETF is
		    March 1.  Numbers shown in square brackets indicate the
		    expected number of weeks at each step.

		    <list style="hanging">
			<t hangText="0."> BEGIN Eight Months Prior to First
				IETF (approx. June 1); Internet Society
				President appoints the Chair.  The appointment
				must be done no later than the Second IETF or
				eight months prior to the First IETF, whichever
				comes first.  The Chair must be announced and
				recognized during a plenary session of the
				Second IETF. [0] </t>

			<t hangText="1."> The Chair establishes and announces
				milestones to ensure the timely selection of the
				nominating committee members. [1] </t>

			<t hangText="2."> The Chair contacts the IESG, IAB,
				and Internet Society Board of Trustees
				and requests a liaison.  The Chair contacts
				the prior year's Chair and requests an
				advisor.  The Chair obtains the list of IESG,
				IAB, and IAOC open positions and descriptions
				from the IETF Executive Director. [0] </t>

			<t hangText="3."> The Chair announces the solicitation
				for voting volunteer members that must remain
				open for at least 30 days.  The announcement
				must be done no later than seven months and two
				weeks prior to the First IETF (approx. June
				15). [6] </t>

			<t hangText="4."> After the solicitation closes the
				Chair announces the pool of volunteers and the
				date of the random selection, which must be at
				least one week in the future.  The announcement
				must be done no later than six months and two
				weeks prior to the First IETF (approx. July
				15). [1] </t>

			<t hangText="5."> On the appointed day the random
				selection occurs and the Chair announces the
				members of the committee and the one week
				challenge period.  The announcement must be done
				no later than six months and one week prior to
				the First IETF (approx. July 22). [1] </t>

			<t hangText="6."> During the challenge period the Chair
				contacts each of the committee members and
				confirms their availability to participate.
				[0] </t>

			<t hangText="7."> After the challenge period closes the
				Chair announces the members of the committee and
				its term begins.  The announcement must be done
				no later than six months prior to the First
				IETF (approx. August 1). [1] </t>

			<t hangText="8."> The committee has one month during
				which it is to self-organize in preparation for
				completing its assigned duties.  This must be
				done no later than five months prior to the
				First IETF (approx. September 15). [6] </t>

			<t hangText="9."> END the Committee Member Selection
				Process; BEGIN the Selection of Candidates; Time
				is at least five months prior to the First IETF
				(approx. September 22). [0] </t>

			<t hangText="10."> The Chair establishes and announces
				the milestones to ensure the timely selection of
				the candidates, including a call for nominations
				for the open positions.  The announcement must
				be done no later than five months prior to the
				First IETF (approx. October 1). [1] </t>

			<t hangText="11."> Over the next three months the
				nominating committee collects input and
				deliberates.  It should plan to conduct
				interviews and other consultations during the
				Third IETF.  The committee is due to complete
				its candidate selection no later than two
				months prior to the First IETF (approx. January
				1). [17] </t>

			<t hangText="12."> END the Selection of Candidates;
				BEGIN the Confirmation of Candidates; Time is
				at least two months prior to the First IETF
				(approx. January 1); [0] </t>

			<t hangText="13."> The committee presents its candidates
				to their respective confirming bodies.  The
				presentation must be done no later than two
				months prior to the First IETF (approx.
				January 1). [0] </t>

			<t hangText="14."> The confirming bodies have one month
				to deliberate and, in communication with the
				nominating committee, accept or reject
				candidates. [4] </t>

			<t hangText="15."> The Chair notifies advises
				unsuccessful nominees that they have not been
				selected. [1] </t>
			
			<t hangText="16."> The Chair announces the confirmed
				candidates.  The announcement must be done no
				later than one month prior to the First IETF
				(approx. February 1). [4] </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="thanks" title="Acknowledgments">
		<t> A great deal of work went into the RFCs that preceded
		    this one.  The 2014 nominating committee and this editor
		    would like to thank all of them once again for the time
		    and energy it took to get us to where we are now.  In
		    no particular order, we acknowledge:

		    <figure><artwork>
  Jeff Case           Fred Baker        John Curran
  Guy Almes           Geoff Huston      Mike St. Johns
  Donald Eastlake     Avri Doria        Bernard Adoba
  Ted T'so            Phil Roberts      Jim Galvin
  Harald Alvestrand   Leslie Daigle     Joel Halpern
  Thomas Narten       Spencer Dawkins   Barry Leiba
  Lars Eggert         Ross Callon       Brian Carpenter
  Robert Elz          Bernie Hoeneisen  John Klensin
  Danny McPherson     S. Moonesamy      Scott Bradner
  Ralph Droms         Pekka Savola
		    </artwork></figure> </t>

		<t> Allison Mankin and Russ White provided early reviews
		    and feedback about this document. </t>

		<t> Jari Arkko was very helpful by independently verifying
		    that the previous text from all the merged documents was
		    marshaled correctly into this one, and Adrian Farrell
		    and Brian Carpenter caught the nits that fell through
		    the cracks. </t>
	</section>
</back>

</rfc>
