<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY RFC1321 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1321.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC1818 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1818.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2026 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2026.xml">
  <!ENTITY RFC2104 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2104.xml">
]>

<rfc ipr="trust200902" category="bcp" obsoletes="3967" updates="2026"
        docName="draft-kucherawy-rfc3967bis-01">

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc toc="yes" ?>
<?rfc tocdepth="2" ?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc rfcedstyle="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>

<front>
	<title abbrev="DownRefs">
		Clarifying when Standards Track Documents may Refer 
		Normatively to Documents at a Lower Level
	</title>

	<author initials="M. S." surname="Kucherawy"
	        fullname="Murray S. Kucherawy"
		role="editor">

		<organization/> 

		<address>
			<postal>
				<street>270 Upland Drive</street>
				<city>San Francisco</city>
				<region>CA</region>
				<code>94127</code>
				<country>United States</country>
			</postal>

			<email>superuser@gmail.com</email>
		</address>
	</author>

	<date year="2015"/>

	<area>General</area>

<keyword>example</keyword>

	<abstract>
		<t> IETF procedures generally require that a standards track RFC
		    may not have a normative reference to another standards track
		    document at a lower maturity level or to a non standards track
		    specification (other than specifications from other standards
		    bodies).  For example, a standards track document may not have
		    a normative reference to an informational RFC.  Exceptions to
		    this rule are sometimes needed as the IETF uses informational
		    RFCs to describe non-IETF standards or IETF-specific modes of
		    use of such standards.  This document clarifies and updates 
		    the procedure used in these circumstances.   </t>
	</abstract>
</front>

<middle>
	<section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
		<t> The Internet Standards Process <xref target="RFC2026"/>
		    Section 4.2.4 specifies the following:

		    <figure><artwork>
  Standards track specifications normally must not depend on other
  standards track specifications which are at a lower maturity level
  or on non standards track specifications other than referenced
  specifications from other standards bodies.
		    </artwork></figure> </t>
		
		<t> One intent is to avoid creating a perception that a standard
		    is more mature than it actually is.  </t>

		<t> It should also be noted that Best Current Practice
		    documents <xref target="RFC1818"/> have generally been
		    considered similar to Standards Track documents in terms
		    of what they can reference.  For example, a normative reference
		    to an Experimental RFC has been considered an improper reference
		    per <xref target="RFC2026"/>. </t>

		<section anchor="normative" title="Normative References">
			<t> Within an RFC, references to other documents fall into
			    two general categories: "normative" and "informative".
			    Broadly speaking, a normative reference specifies a
			    document that must be read to fully understand or
			    implement the subject matter in the new RFC, or whose
			    contents are effectively part of the new RFC, as its
			    omission would leave the new RFC incompletely
			    specified.  An informative reference is not normative;
			    rather, it provides only additional background
			    information. </t>

			<t> An exact and precise definition of what is (and is not)
			    a normative reference has proven challenging in practice,
			    as the details and implications can be subtle.  Moreover,
			    whether a reference needs to be normative can depend on
			    the context in which a particular RFC is being published
			    in the first place.  For example, in the context of an
			    IETF Standard, it is important that all dependent pieces
			    be clearly specified and available in an archival form
			    so that there is no disagreement over what constitutes a
			    standard.  This is not always the case for other
			    documents. </t>

			<t> The rest of this section provides guidance on what
			    might (and might not) be considered normative in the
			    context of the IETF standards process. </t>

			<t> In the IETF, it is a basic assumption that implementors
			    must have a clear understanding of what they need to
			    implement in order to be fully compliant with a standard
			    and to be able to interoperate with other
			    implementations of that standard.  For documents that
			    are referenced, any document that includes key
			    information an implementer needs would be normative.
			    For example, if one needs to understand a packet format
			    defined in another document in order to fully implement
			    a specification, the reference to that format would be
			    normative.  Likewise, if a reference to a required
			    algorithm is made, the reference would be normative. </t>

			<t> Some specific examples:

			    <list style="symbols">
				<t> If a protocol relies on IPsec to provide
				    security, one cannot fully implement the
				    protocol unless the specification for IPsec
				    is available; hence, the reference would be
				    normative.  The referenced specification would
				    likely include details about specific key
				    management requirements, which transforms are
				    required and which are optional, etc. </t>

				<t> In MIB documents, an IMPORTS clause by
				    definition is a normative reference.  When a
				    reference to an example is made, such a
				    reference need not be normative.  For example,
				    text such as "an algorithm such as the one
				    specified in [RFCxxxx] would be acceptable"
				    indicates an informative reference, since that
				    cited algorithm is just one of several possible
				    algorithms that could be used. </t>
			    </list> </t>
		</section>
	</section>

	<section anchor="the_need" title="The Need for Downward References">
		<t> There are a number of circumstances in which an IETF document
		    may need to make a normative reference to a document at a lower
		    maturity level, but such a reference conflicts with Section
		    4.2.4 of <xref target="RFC2026"/>.  For example:

		    <list style="symbols">
			<t> A standards track document may need to refer to a
			    protocol or algorithm developed by an external body but
			    modified, adapted, or profiled by an IETF informational
			    RFC, for example, MD5 <xref target="RFC1321"/> and
			    HMAC <xref target="RFC2104"/>.  Note that this does not
			    override the IETF's duty to see that the specification
			    is indeed sufficiently clear to enable creation of
			    interoperable implementations.  </t>

			<t> A standards document may need to refer to a proprietary
			    protocol, and the IETF normally documents proprietary
			    protocols using informational RFCs. </t>

			<t> A migration or co-existence document may need to define
			    a standards track mechanism for migration from, and/or
			    co-existence with, an historic protocol, a proprietary
			    protocol, or possibly a non-standards track
			    protocol. </t>

			<t> There are exceptional procedural or legal reasons that
			    force the target of the normative reference to be an
			    informational or historical RFC or to be at a
			    lower standards level than the referring document. </t>

			<t> A BCP document may want to describe best current
			    practices for experimental or informational
			    specifications. </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section title="procedure" title="The Procedure to Be Used">
		<t> For Standards Track or BCP documents requiring normative
		    reference to documents of lower maturity, the relevant working
		    group, the responsible Area Director, and the IESG as a whole
		    should be aware of the down reference and will exercise
		    their judgment.  Ideally, the normal IETF Last Call procedure
		    will be followed, with the need for the down reference
		    explicitly documented in the Last Call itself.  Any community
		    comments on the appropriateness of down references will be
		    considered by the IESG as part of its judgment. </t>

		<t> Document shepherds and responsible Area Directors will typically
		    ensure that the document itself, or the Document Shepherd writeup
		    or other supporting information accompanying the document,
		    includes adequate information explaining why the down reference
		    is appropriate. </t>

		<t> Once a specific down reference to a particular document has been
		    accepted by the community (e.g., has been mentioned in several
		    Last Calls), an Area Director may waive subsequent notices in
		    the Last Call of down references to it.  This should only occur
		    when the same document (and version) are being referenced and
		    when the AD believes that the document's use is an accepted part
		    of the community's understanding of the relevant technical
		    area.  For example, the use of MD5 <xref target="RFC1321"/> and
		    HMAC <xref target="RFC2104"/> is well known among
		    cryptographers. </t>

		<t> This procedure should not be used if the proper step is to move
		    the document to which the reference is being made into the
		    appropriate category.  It is not intended as an easy way out of
		    normal process.  Rather, the procedure is intended for dealing
		    with specific cases where putting particular documents into
		    the required category is problematic and unlikely ever to
		    happen. </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="sec" title="Security Considerations">
		<t> This document is not known to create any new vulnerabilities
		    for the Internet.  On the other hand, inappropriate or
		    excessive use of the process might be considered a downgrade
		    attack on the quality of IETF standards or, worse, on the
		    rigorous review of security aspects of standards. </t>
	</section>
</middle>

<back>
	<references title="Normative References">
		&RFC2026;
	</references>

	<references title="Informative References">
		&RFC1321;
		&RFC1818;
		&RFC2104;
	</references>

	<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgments">
		<t> The author wishes to thank the following for reviews and
		    comments on this draft:
		    Barry Leiba,
		    (others) </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="changes1" title="Changes Since RFC3967">
		<t> <list style="symbols">
			<t> None (yet). </t>
		    </list> </t>
	</section>

	<section anchor="changes2" title="Changes History">
		<section title="RFC3967 to -00">
			<t> <list style="symbols">
				<t> Convert to xml2rfc. </t>

				<t> Reset Acknowledgments. </t>
			    </list> </t>
		</section>

		<section title="-00 to -01">
			<t> <list style="symbols">
				<t> Updates RFC2026. </t>
			    </list> </t>
		</section>
	</section>
</back>

</rfc>
